Why did the
из-за чего так сильно после вторжения
ruble drop so much against the dollar after Russia's invasion of Ukraine?
России в Украины просел рубль по
Do you think the war that
доллару Как вы считаете э война которую
Putin unleashed in Ukraine was positive,
Путин развязал в Украине положительна
negative, or did not have any impact on
отрицательна или никак не повлияла на
your life in
вашу жизнь в
Kemerovo Well, personally, it did
Кемерово Ну вот лично на мою жизнь
not affect my life at all did not affect  Yes,
вообще никак не повлияло не повлияло Да
you
вы яйца
eat eggs Well, yes, eggs have gone up in price, your prices
едите Ну да яйца подорожали у вас
have gone up, well, not enough to
подорожали ну не настолько чтобы
raise the dollar on this hype, the price of
поднимать на этом хайпа доллар подорожал
rocks would have gone up
скал бы
so not much
так не намного
as far as he knows, he knows, well, he jumps up and
насколько он знаете он знае ну он скачет
down, no matter how well,
то вниз то вверх как бы ну как не
let’s say how old he was before the war,
Давайте до войны сколько он был
70  No, you know,
70 Не ну вот знаете вот
if you take
если брать
the moments, as far as I remember, the dollar was 130
моменты насколько я помню доллар 130
rubles, and so it cost 30 until 14 When
рублей вот а так 30 он стоил до 14 Когда
you first attacked Ukraine, this
вы первый раз напали на Украину это ещё
was before the war, long before the war, it was
было до войны за долго до войны он стол
n’t a table. Just before the fourteenth year
не Вот как раз до четырнадцатого года у
you
вас
had  Don’t look at the same moment such that
был Не смотрите тот же момент такой что
inflation is all business for the dollar, well
инфляция все дела у доллара ж тоже
inflation is also going right Well, why did
инфляция идёт правильно Ну из-за чего у
you have such high
вас пошла такая большая
inflation? So we don’t have big inflation Well,
инфляция Так у нас большой инфляции то
no, look, the dollar was 30
нет Ну как нет смотре доллар был 30
then 70 then weaving I’m I’m talking about  world
потом 70 потом сотка я я я про мировую
inflation, I say this: world inflation
инфляцию говорю так мировая инфляция Ну
Well, look, if you have inflation in
так смотрите если у вас инфляция по
relation to dollars and you, uh, the ruble
отношению к долларам да и у вас ээ рубль
is falling, then the dollar is not as susceptible to
падает значит доллар не и так подвержен
inflation as the ruble, that is, in the world currencies
инфляции как рубль то есть в мире валюты
undergo inflation Yes, the process of inflation, but
проходят инфляцию Да процесс инфляции но
not with this, not with this  percentage
не с такой не с таким процентом
level I would say, on the contrary, the
уровнем Я бы знаете сказал наоборот
dollar is less susceptible to inflation than
доллар он менее подвержен инфляции Чем
all other currencies in the world. Why? Well,
все остальные валюты в мире А
for now it’s a world currency. Yeah,
почему Ну пока что это мировая валюта
I understand. But that’s why the ruble
Угу понял А вот из-за чего так сильно
sank so much against the dollar after Russia’s invasion of Ukraine.
после вторжение России в Украины просел
only the ruble, you,
доллару так а не только рубль вы вы же
other currencies are not tracked. Well,
другие валюту не отслеживается Ну
for example, the euro did not drop by 30%, but the
например евро не просело на 30% а а а
Japanese yen,
японская иена
let’s say the Japanese Yen did not drop by 30%
допустим японская Ена не просела на 30%
against the
по отношению к
dollar. Well, not by 30, but it dropped by
доллару Ну не на 30 но просела на
how much. Well, right now I can’t tell you
сколько Ну вот прям сейчас я вам сказать
can you go on a spree at the same time When the
могу вы заодно загули Когда началась
war started and
война и
when at the
когда на данный
moment
момент
[music]
[музыка]
pgd so we look at the exchange rate
пгд так вот смотрим курс
uh so 100 Japanese ein dollars
ээ так 100 японских ейн доллары
so almost doesn’t
так вообще почти не
change at all enu I just
меняется ену Это я просто как приме
quoted it as an example so well look Well so the
привёл так вот ну смотрите Ну так
fluctuation look look again look  are
колебание смотрите смотри ещё раз смотри
you relevant in this area or not? Here
актуально вы в этой сфере или нет Вот
I am making a graph for 5 years, yes Yeah, there are no
делаю зап за 5 лет график да Угу нету
such fluctuations so that it would be like in Russia,
таких колебаний чтобы было как в России
there is 30% for 2
там по 30% за 2
years. Look at the
года Посмотрите
francs What to
франки Что
see francs Whose
посмотреть франки Чьи
francs Frank Frank of which country
франки Франк Франк какой страны
Frank, well, you can look at any country of
Франк ну можете посмотреть любой страны
which country  The
какой страны
French franc
Франк Франции
is acceptable If you also
допустим Если бы ты ещё швейцарский
said the Swiss franc Let's see, just for
франк сказал Давай посмотрим вот ради
fun, let's look at the rate of the French
интереса смотрим курс французского
Franc
Франка
Yes, and that's where we'll finish our economic
Да и на этом закончим нашу экономическую
theory Let's look at the French Franc Let's
теорию Давай французский Франк Смотрим
talk Let's see, let's see, I
Да гулим Ну давайте посмотрим давай я
understand from your intonation What is
так понимаю по вашей интонации Что такое
such a currency There is no currency  not now we
такой Валюты нет в при не сейчас мы
’ll look
посмотрим
like this Now we’ll look at the French
так Сейчас мы посмотрим так французский
Franc I think we’ll also look at the German subsidiary mark
Франк Я думаю ещё немецкую доч марку мы
against the
посмотрим к
dollar Well, that’s the German currency
доллару Ну это же немецкая валюта
right Yes, well, we
правильно Да да ну и французский Франк
’ll look at the French Franc not just like that,
посмотрим не просто вот так вот
mock
насмехайтесь надо
me in the sense that it’s like Well, no  so
мной в том плане что как бы Ну не то
that it’s unpleasant for me, as if it does
чтобы мне это неприятно как бы мне на
n’t really matter to me, I don’t think you were thinking when you said
разницы не я думал вы когда сказали
Frank I was thinking about the Swiss franc Yes, as I understand it, you’re not even wholesale Frank of
Франк Я дума про швейцарский франк Да я
which country you wanted to say And
какой страны вы хотели сказать И
what do you know, the Frank is not the most
какой знаете Франк - это не самая
popular currency  in the world it’s actually
популярная валюта в мире на самом деле
shorter than
короче
Dimon-16 up to held dollars held well. For
димон-16 до держал доллары держал хорошо
example, francs or German daughter marks
А например франки или немецкие доч марки
When you, like, held in your hands never,
Когда вы типа держали в руках никогда
personally, I never held
вот лично я никогда не держал
why Well, it happened so I
почему Ну так сложилось
understood and in which countries do I
понял а на территории каких стран
accept French francs for
принимают французские франки в
circulation?  I can tell you, I’m not
оборот я тебе могу сказать я не
that good at economics, that’s how it is, let’s
настолько под в экономике вот как
say here you are Where
допустим вот тыя навите од Где
French francs are a means of
французские франки есть средством
payment Well, perhaps France I may have called
платежа Ну возможно Франция Я может быть
incorrectly I may have
неправильно выз Я возможно неправильно
howled
выл Ну как ты
incorrectly Well, how wrong are you, I can admit my mistake
неправильно я могу признать свою ошибку
as if you were there, it’s okay In  what’s the
как бы вы там ничего страшно В чём
mistake what’s the mistake Well, I don’t know, you’re
ошибку в чём ошибку Ну не знаю вот ты
making fun of this like that. I’m
вот над этим так насмехается вот Я вот
sitting quietly right now, I’m not googling, they
сейчас сижу спокойно я не гуглю там на
actually ate French Franc.
самом деле ели французский Франк
Perhaps it’s like France there - this is the
Возможно там вот как бы Франция - это
European Union there. Perhaps yes,
Евросоюз там там Возможно да
this is actually the euro in  in everyday life the meaning
это на самом деле евро в обиходе в смыс
is not not the euro in the
не не евро в
European Union is not the euro - Well, this comes from the word
Евросоюзе не евро - Это ж от слова
European Union. And in France there is probably a
Евросоюз А во Франции наверное
French
французский
Franc and France is not in the European Union. Well, for
Франк а Франция не в Евросоюзе
example, look at Poland in
получается Ну например смотри Польша в
the European Union, but it has zlotys,
Евросоюзе но у неё ж есть злотые
Polish
польские
zlotys. Well, you know, in Ukraine there is,
злотые Ну знаешь вот в Украине есть
let’s say, hryvnia  Ana, she’s kind of in
допустим гривня Ана она как бы типа в
the European Union, we’re not in the European Union. Well,
Евросоюзе не мы не в Евросоюзе Ну
for example, in Poland you see there are both euros and
например в Польше видите есть и евро и
zlotys, but it turns out they can walk,
злоты да получается как бы могут ходить
but in France it turns out that they walk and the French franc, you do
а во Франции получается ходит и Франк
n’t know, your
французский не вот знаешь вот твоя
logic is a little wrong here, in
логика маленько здесь неправильная на
fact, you want to say
самом деле хочешь сказать
why Well, you know, take napkins, wipe away your tears,
почему Ну ты знаешь возьми салфетки утри
please, in fact, you
слёзы пожалуйста на самом деле в трусах
’re sitting in your underpants. Why not, I’m sitting at home,
сидишь А почему нет я у себя дома сижу
[ __ ], you’re not an economist,
[__] не у тебя экономист
[ __ ], but I’m not saying that I’m
[__] так а я не говорю что я
an economist. Let’s think about you.
экономист Давайте об ты думаешь Вот
Here in the chat roulettes are sitting, just look about
здесь в чат рулетки сидят прям смотри об
exclusively economists and you directly know
исключительно экономисты и прямо знаешь
such people of subtly soulful
такие люди тонко душевной
nationality soulful
национально душенко душевной
nationality. Look, for example, I just
национальности Смотри я например просто
live in the city of vibrant Czechoslovakians.
сам проживаю в городе бурно чехословаки
Yes, and I’m more interested in the exchange rate of the
Да и меня более интересует курс
Czechoslovak koruna Yes to the Soviet
чехословацкой кроны Да к Советскому
ruble
рублю